Mss.917.3.R76
American Philosophical Society
Etats-Unis d'amerique
Circa 1837
Mss.917.3.R76
American Philosophical Society
2.0 Volume(s)
A published first edition, 1837, of Jean Baptiste Gaspard Roux de Rochelle’s History of the United States of America, in French, with a companion volume of original sketches used for the 96 engraved plates. Sketches are of American scenes and history, some apparently original, others after de Bry and other artists, all used in Roux de rochelle's book.
2 volumes.
Roux de Rochelle, 1762-1849
Volume 1-2
Biographical/Historical note
Elected to the APS in 1836, Roux de Rochelle served as French minister to the United States from 1829-1831.
Scope and Contents note
Native American Images note: 27 original drawings of Native Americans and 27 steel engravings of the same for Roux de Rochelle’s Etats-Unis d’Amerique. Indigenous people, primarily from the southern states, in native attire depicted as hunting, fishing, playing, mourning, warring, eating, cooking, and celebrating. Some illustrations accompanying the early text are based on Theodore DeBry’s engravings of John White’s watercolor drawings of Roanoke Island in 1585. With the later historical text are illustrations of Oneidas, Mohawks, and Delawares conferring or warring with Europeans. Also, sketches of petroglyphs, pottery, wampum, and headgear. Illustrators and engravers include Vernier, Branche, and Milbert.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Both volumes presented by the author.
Early American History Note
These two bound volumes contain a printed copy of Jean Baptiste Gaspard Roux de Rochelle Etats-Unis D'Amerique, a Frenchman’s take on American history and culture, and a volume that contains what appears to be drafts of the images that were printed in the book. Many of the images in the second volume appear to be based upon more well-known works of art. Some are in color.
Art; Delaware Indians; Engravings.; Foreign Language; Illustrations.; Indians of North America--Florida; Indians of North America--North Carolina; Literature, Arts, and Culture; Lumbee Indians; Mohawk Indians; Oneida Indians; Printed Material; Seminole Indians; Sketchbooks; Sketches.; Southeast Indians
- No.1 Guerriers Indiens, 1837
- No.2 Declaration de guerre, 1837
- No.3 Ceremonies avant le depart pour la guerre, 1837
  - Ceremony for a departed Seminole, 1837
- No.4 Trophies apres la victoire, 1837
- No.5 Colonne erigee par Ribaut en 1562, 1837
- No.6 Deuil et supplication des Veuves, 1837
  - Seminole widows, 1837
- No.7 Pont naturel de Virginie, 1837
- No.8 Jeune fille, mere de famille, Vieillard (Femmes indiennes et Vieillard), 1837
- No.9 Foret (Chute d'eau pres les bains de Schooley), 1837
- No.10 Danse, 1837
- No.11 Exercices de la jeunesse, 1837
- No.12 Bapteme des anabaptiste, 1837
- No.13 Chasse aux alligators, 1837
- No.14 Chasse aux cerfs, 1837
- No.15 Maniere de fumer les chairs des animaux (Maniere de fumer le gibier), 1837
- No.16 Preparation des mets et repas Indiens (Repas et preparation des mets), 1837
- No.17 Traitement des malades (Maniere de traiter les malades), 1837
- No.18 Passage des rivieres (Passage des rivieres a Gue), 1837
- No.19 Pirogues creusees par l'action du feu (Maniere de creuser les barques)
- No.20 Exercice de la peche, 1837
  - Seminoles fishing, 1837
- No.21 Village Indien entoure de palissades, 1837
- No.22 Guillaume Penn achetant la terre des sauvages, 1837
- No.23 Fleches incendiaires, 1837
- No.24 Le union d'une famille Indienne (Fete autour d'un feu), 1837
  - Delaware celebration, 1837
- No.25 Mais; Tabac, 1837
- No.26 Palissades naturelles de l'Hudson
- No.27 Ocelot; Castor, 1837
- No.28 Wapiti; Buffalo, 1837
- No.29 Premier temple des Quakers a Philadelphie, 1837
- No.30 Premiere Eglise Anabaptiste a Providence, 1837
- No.31 Predication des Anabaptistes, 1837
- No.32 Eglise Episcopale de Richmont, 1837
- No.33 Cathedrale Catholique a Baltimore, 1837
- No.34 Ruines du Fort Ticonderoga, 1837
- No.35 Maison du gouverneur Hollandais a Albani, 1837
- No.36 Conference avec les Indiens autour du feu du conseil (Conference autour du feu du conseil), 1837
  - Debate around council fire, 1837
- No.37 Anciennes fortifications de l'Ohio, 1837
- No.38 Anciennes fortifications, 1837
- No.39 Anciennes fortifications, 1837
- No.40 Inscription et autres antiquites Americaines, 1837
- No.41 Hopital de Pensylvanie, 1837
- No.42 Wampums et coiffure, 1837
  - Wampum and head-dress, 1837
- No.43 Homme emplume, 1837
- No.44 Hotel de ville de Philadelphie, 1837
- No.45 Boston et ses environs, 1837
- No.46 Maison de Johson dans le pays des Mohawks
- No.47 Bocage du conseil - les Indiens Oneidas, 1837
- No.48 Entree de la riviere d'Hudson, 1837
- No.49 Mort de Montgomery devant Quebec, 1837
- No.50 Vue de Boston depart de la flotte Anglaise, 1837
- No.51 Facsimile de quelques signatures de l'acte d'Independance, 1837
- No.52 Plan de la Baie de New York, 1837
- No.53 Washington, 1837
- No.54 Franklin, 1837
- No.55 John Adams, 1837
- No.56 Jefferson, 1837
- No.57 Lac George, 1837
- No.58 Usine de Gleens, 1837
- No.59 Pont sur l'Hudson pres Luzerne, 1837
- No.60 Chute et rapides d'Adleys, 1837
- No.61 Capitulation de Burgoyne a Saratoga, 1837
- No.62 Vue actuelle de Saratoga, 1837
- No.63 Chute d'eau pres le Mont. Ida, 1837
- No.64 Vue de la Ville d'Hudson, 1837
- No.65 Vue de West Point, 1837
- No.66 Jardin de Koscinsco a West Point, 1837
- No.67 Arrestation du Major Andre au Bourg Tarry Town, 1837
- No.68 Desastre de Wyoming, 1837
- No.69 Prise de Pensacola, 1837
- No.70 Capitulation de Cornwallis a York-town, 1837
- No.71 Emigrations vers l'Quest, 1837
- No.72 Defrichemens, 1837
- No.73 Monument de Bunker's-hill, pres de Boston, 1837
- No.74 Museum de Philadelphie, 1837
- No.75 Hotel de Ville de New York, 1837
- No.76 Eglise St. Paul a New York, 1837
- No.77 Cavernes, 1837
- No.78 Sarigue; Serpent a Sonnettes, 1837
- No.79 Inondation du Mississippi, 1837
- No.80 Aigle Pecheur, 1837
- No.81 Universite de Cambridge pres Boston, 1837
- No.82 Universite de Philadelphie, 1837
- No.83 Institut de Franklin, 1837
- No.84 Banque de Stephen Gerard, 1837
- No.85 Penitentiare de Philadelphie, 1837
- No.86 Plan de Penitentiare, 1837
- No.87 Universite de Virginie, 1837
- No.88 College de Kenion (Etats de l'Ohio), 1837
- No.89 Capitole de Washington, 1837
- No.90 Presidence, 1837
- No.91 Departemens d'Etats, 1837
- No.92 Tombeau du Washington a Mont. Vernon, 1837
- No.93 Rapides et rochers du Mohawk, 1837
- No.94 Vue du Lac Erie, 1837
- No.95 Saut du Niagara, 1837
- No.96 Voute sous la Chute du Niagara, 1837